Guide to the Rush Benjamin Wheeler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Rush Benjamin Wheeler papers
1869-1966
1869-1871
MS 1148
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
Writings and lecture notes taken while he was a student at Yale University and correspondence concerning the alumni of the Yale Class of 1871.
Wheeler, Rush Benjamin, 1844-1930
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cleora B. Wheeler, 1947 and 1951.
Biographical / Historical
Rush Benjamin Wheeler, B.A. 1871.
Born January 29, 1844, in South Butler, New York.
Died April 2, 1930, in St. Paul, Minnesota.
Father, Orange Hall Wheeler, a fruit farmer; son of Eli and Grizel (Osborn) Wheeler, of New Fairfield, Conn. Mother, Eve (Tucker) Wheeler; daughter of Dr. Benjamin Tucker, Jr., and Eve (Viele) Tucker, of Butler, New York. Private school in South Butler and Cazenovia (New York) Seminary: Second colloquy appointment Junior year; first colloquy appointment Senior year; member Gamma Nu.
Taught natural sciences and mathematics at South Berkshire Institute, New Marlboro, Massachusetts, 1871-1872; secretary of Remington Mowing Machine Company, at Ilion, New York, 1872-73; then moved to Austin, Minnesota, and studied law under his brother, Eber Osborn Wheeler, and acted as his assistant until 1876; member of firm of E. O. and R. B. Wheeler (law and land, business) April, 1876-February, 1880, being, admitted to Minnesota Bar March 23, 1877; continued in the law, real estate, loans, and insurance business in Austin until 1883 and then in St. Paul until his retirement in July, 1923; director of First National Bank of Austin, 1880-1883; president of Real Estate Board of St. Paul 1894-1896 and its treasurer 1900-1904; elected honorary member of the board 1923; director of Chamber of Commerce of St. Paul 1885-1900; Secretary of Summit Avenue Improvement Association 1886; treasurer of St. Paul Y.M.C.A 1888-1903; trustee of Park Congregational Church St. Paul for over fifteen years and treasurer for about ten; member National Association of Real Estate Boards and charter member (in 1918) Athletic Club of St. Paul.
Married May 17, 1876, in Rochester, Minnesota, Harriet Sophia, daughter of Asa Spaulding Clark, Jr., and Rhoda (Shaw) Clark, Children: Frost Montaine, or, Cleora Clark (B.A. University of Minnesota 1903); Everett Clark (died at nine years of age); and Ross Clark (died at fifteen years of age). Death due to chronic myocarditis with complications. Buried in Oakland Cemetery, St. Paul.
Survived by wife, daughter, one son, and three grandchildren.
Yale College Obituary Record, 1929-1930, pages 25-26.
Scope and Contents
Writings and lecture notes taken while he was a student at Yale University and correspondence concerning the alumni of the Yale Class of 1871.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Wheeler, Rush Benjamin, 1844-1930; Yale University -- Alumni and alumnae; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory, (1869-1871)-1966; 0.25; (1 box)
  - RBW's student papers, Circa 1869-1871
    General note
    Probably written in his Junior and Senior years. No. 18 is dated October 18, 1869. No. 10 is dated February 23, 1871.
    - 1. Cheerfulness and Levity (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 2. Ideality (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 3. Mental Culture (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General
      On the last page he addresses "Fellow members of the Lycaum."
    - 4. Patriotism (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 5. Selfishness (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 6. Success (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 7. Truth (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 8. The Byron Mystery (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 9. Jesuits in America (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 10. Modern Chemistry (2-23-1871) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 11. "Our Country is the Best" (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 12. Principle Involved in the Revolution of 1688 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 13. Rebecca and Rowena (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 14. Religion of the Romans in the Time of Cicero (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 15. Rise of Chivalry (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 16. Sir Roger de Coverly (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 17. Suns (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 18. Ought a Legislator to be Bound by the will of his Constitutents? (First Dispute, October 16, 1869). (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 19. Ought the Mormons to be Prohibited by Law? (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 20. Is Prussian Education Better than That in the United States? (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 21. Life of Cicero (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 22. Character of Cicero (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 23. Life of Virgil (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - RBW's senior year notebooks, Nos. 1-5, 1870-1871
    - No. 1, 1871
      - Science of History (8 lectures) (Box 1, Folder 3)
        First lecture by President Woolsey
        Balance by Professor Wheeler
        3rd.: How to Study History
        7th: Germany
        16th: Switzerland
        17th: Scandinavia
        18th: Henry VII.
        September 19, 1870 through fall months of 1870. (Continued in notebook #2.)
      - Natural Theology (1 lecture, "Relation of Soul to Matter" by Professor Noah Porter, Clark Professor of Moral Law and Metaphysics. September 19, 1870.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
        This course was taken in January 1871. See notebook #3. 25 lectures.
    - No. 2, 1871
      - Science of History (17 lectures) (#19-35 inclusive. Continued from notebook #1). (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Given by Professor Wheeler.
        19th: Henry VIII
        25th: Calvin
        28th: The Netherlands
        31st: Philip
        34th; Spain, France, England
        35th: Elizabeth
        January 9, presumably through March 17, 1871. (Continued in notebook #3)
      - German (1 lecture), September 20, 1870. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - No. 3, 1871
      - Science of History (6 lectures) "Third Term": (#36-41 inclusive. Continued from notebook #2.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Lecture 36: French History
        Lecture 40 (5th): Charles IX
        Lecture 41 (6th): Henry IV.
        May 15, presumably, through June 23. 1871. Lecture 31 is dated May 17, 1871.
      - Natural Theology (25 lectures) (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Given by Professor Noah Porter, Clark Professor of Moral Law and Metaphysics, (Lecture 25 is on "The Choice of a Profession," "All the duties which we owe our fellow men are grounded on the duty of a benevolent regard for their highest good.")
        January 7 through March 31, 1871.
    - No. 4, 1871
      - Political Philosophy (11 lectures) (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Given by President Theodore D. Woolsey, January 9, through February 16, 1871, and (6 lectures)
        Given by President Woolsey:
        Lecture 1: Treaty of Weetphalia
        Lecture 3: Peace of Utrecht
        Lecture 4: "Holy Alliance"
        May 1, through May 1871.
      - Medical Lectures (16 lectures) (Box 1, Folder 3)
        February 27, through March 24, 1871.
      - Botany (9 lectures) (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Given by Professor Eaton, May 6, through June 29, 1871.
    - No. 5, 1871
      - Geology (11 lectures) (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Given by Professor James D. Dana, Silliman Professor of Geology and Minerology.
        Lectures 8: Genesis
        Lectures 9, 10 and 11: Darwinism. March 1 through June 27, 1871.
      - Roman Law (10 lectures) (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Given by Professor James Hadley, Professor of the Greek Language and Literature.
        April 28, through May 15, 1871.
      - Roman Law (continued) (14 lectures) (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Given by Simeon E. Baldwin
        May 16, through June 8, 1871.
      - Science of Language (6 lectures) (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Given by Professor William D. Whitney, Professor of Sanskrit and Modern Languages.
        June 9, through June 26, 1871, presumably. Lecture 5 was on June 22, 1871.
  - Correspondence re members of the Class of 1871, 1924-1938, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)